{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct ?", "opta": "Snow albedo falls at all wave length with the increase of grain size", "optb": "The effect of grain size on reflection is maximum in the near-IR region", "optc": "The effect of grain size on reflection is low in the visible region of the spectrum", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The refractive index of the ocean water:", "opta": "increases with salinity", "optb": "increases with temperature", "optc": "decreases with salinity", "optd": "decreases with temperature", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The arrangement of terrain features which provides attributes: the shape, size and texture of objects, is called :", "opta": "spectral variation", "optb": "spatial variation", "optc": "temporal variation", "optd": "None of these .", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Electromagnetic radiation :", "opta": "produces a time varying magnetic field and vice versa", "optb": "once generated, remains self-propagat-ing.", "optc": "is capable to travel across space", "optd": "consists of magnetic and electric fields", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the important characteristic of a target which facilitates its identification from the following:", "opta": "spectral variation", "optb": "spatial variation", "optc": "temporal variation", "optd": "polarisation variation", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following frequency regions is a part of sun's radiation?", "opta": "Ultraviolet frequency region", "optb": "Visible frequency region", "optc": "Infrared frequency region", "optd": "Radio frequency region", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The instruments which provide electromagnetic radiation of specified wave length or a band of wave lengths to illuminate the earth surface, are called :", "opta": "sensonrs", "optb": "passive sensors", "optc": "active sensors", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Due to pertubation of the orbit, satellite orbit parameters are frequently updated on measurements carried out by its", "opta": "six ground stations", "optb": "five ground stations", "optc": "four ground stations", "optd": "three ground stations", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Coherence of two electromagnetic waves takes place if their phase difference is :", "opta": "constant in time", "optb": "constant in space", "optc": "constant in time and space", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The part radiation due to scattered/diffused radiation entering the field of view of a remote sensor other than that from the required target,", "opta": "reduces the contrast of the image and also its sharpness", "optb": "increases the contrast of the image but reduces the sharpness", "optc": "increases both the contrast and sharpness", "optd": "reduces the contrast but increases the sharpness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following residual biases involves the GPS accuracy ?", "opta": "Satellite dependent baises due to uncertainty in the orbital parameters of the satellite.", "optb": "Receiver-depandent biases due to clock stability with line", "optc": "Signal propagation baises due to the sphere and troposphere propogation.", "optd": "All the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct definition from the following with response to GIS.", "opta": "Common boundry between two areas of a locality is known as adjacency.", "optb": "The area features which are wholly contained within another area feature, is known so containment.", "optc": "The geometric property which describes the linkage between line features is defined as connectivity.", "optd": "All of these.", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following errors is produced by platform characteristics of the sensor ?", "opta": "altitude variation", "optb": "altitude", "optc": "orbit drift", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coherence length over which there is a strong relationship between amplitudes is;", "opta": "directly proportional to the bandwidth", "optb": "inversely proportional to the bandwidth", "optc": "the square of the bandwidth", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the given figure the phase of", "opta": "crest A is \u03c0/2", "optb": "B crossing is \u03c0", "optc": "trough C is 3 \u03c0/2", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If 0 is the angle of scan measured from the nadir, the ground distance swept by the sensor IFOV is proportional to :", "opta": "sin2\u03b8", "optb": "cos2\u03b8", "optc": "sec2\u03b8", "optd": "tan2\u03b8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct regarding the GPS satellites ?", "opta": "The nominal altitude is about 20, 200 km", "optb": "The inclination of axis satellite is 55\u00b0", "optc": "The satellite transmits two L band signals (L1 with 1575.42 MHz and L2 with 1276.6 MHz)", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Indian space effort started in 1962 with the establishment of a rocket.", "optb": "Development of space (DOS) was established by the Government of India in 1972", "optc": "Indian Space Research Organisation (ISRO) is responsible for the space technology and its application to various activities.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Rayleigh's criteria for a rough surface is: (where letters carry their usual meanings).", "opta": "h > \u03bb/\u0394 cos \u03b8", "optb": "h = \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "optc": "h > \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "optd": "h < \u03bb/8 cos \u03b8", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "The distance between two successive crests or troughs of a wave, is called, the wave length", "optb": "The wave length is measured in metres and a fraction of a metre", "optc": "The wave length is generally denoted by \u03bb", "optd": "The length of the crest from the mid point, is called amplitude", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The basic requirement of any sensor system, is :", "opta": "radiometric resolution", "optb": "spatial resolution", "optc": "spectral resolution", "optd": "temporal resolution", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following helps to identify the objects on the earth surface ?", "opta": "atmospheric window", "optb": "signature", "optc": "radiometric error", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The spectral region of the electromagnetic radiation which passes through the atmosphere without much attenuation is known as:", "opta": "ozone hole", "optb": "atmospheric window", "optc": "ozone window", "optd": "black hole", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "During the day, earth reflects solar radiation", "optb": "During the day earth reflects both solar radiation the emission from its surface", "optc": "During the night, earth emits radiation from its surface", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The remote sensing techniques applied for the earth's surface features, is generally confined to the following wave lengths :", "opta": "0.4 to 1.3, 1.5 to 1.8, 2.2 to 2.6 \u03bcm", "optb": "2.2 to 2.6, 3.0 to 3.6, 4.2 to 5.0 \u03bcm", "optc": "4.2 to 5.0, 7.0 to 15.0 \u03bcm and 1 cm to 30 cm", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The value of energy quantum for radiation of any frequency is proportional to :", "opta": "the frequency", "optb": "the reciprocal of the energy", "optc": "the square of the frequency", "optd": "the square root of the frequency", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The phase difference of the waves 1 and 2 at A in the given figure is :", "opta": "\u03c0/4", "optb": "\u03c0/2", "optc": "\u03c0", "optd": "3\u03c0/2", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A perfectly black body :", "opta": "is a diffuse emitter", "optb": "absorbs all the radiations of every wave lengths", "optc": "emits power of every wave length", "optd": "All the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "When the electric field oscillates in the direction of the electric vector, a plane polarised wave is formed.", "optb": "When the electric vector is in the plane of incidence, vertical polarisation is formed.", "optc": "When the electric vector is at right angles to the plane of incidence, horizontal polarization wave is formed.", "optd": "The plane containing the incident ray and normal to the reflecting surface at the point of incidence is called the plane of incidence.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Phase of a wave is expressed as a fraction of a period with respect to a refrence", "optb": "Phase is usually specified by angular measure with one period being 360\u00b0", "optc": "The reference for finding the phase of a wave is taken from the previous passage through zero from the negative to the positive direction.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A and B are two towers of equal height diametrically opposite on either side of the nadir point, at 3 km and 5 km distances. Which one of the following statements is correct?", "opta": "Height displacement of A will be less than that of B", "optb": "Height displacement of B will be less than that of A", "optc": "Height displacement of A and B is equal", "optd": "Height displacement of A and B will be towards each other", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Remote sensing techniques makes use of the properties of-----emitted, reflected or diffracted by the sensed objects:", "opta": "electric waves", "optb": "soundwaves", "optc": "electromagnetic waves", "optd": "wind waves", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following parameters is accurate for DGPS.", "opta": "Positional accuracies ~ 1 - 2 m if rover is less than 1-2 km from the reference station", "optb": "Positional accuracies ~ 2 - 5m if rover is less than 2-5 fm from the reference station", "optc": "Positional accuracies ~ 5 - 10 m if rover is less than 5-10 km from reference station", "optd": "Positional accuracies ~ 5 - 10 m if rover is less than 25 km", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The most widely used antenna in GPS is", "opta": "Parabolid antenna", "optb": "Microstrip antenna", "optc": "Horn antenna", "optd": "Slotted antenna", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following statements regarding remote sensing is correct.", "opta": "The interaction of the electromagnetic radiation with the target", "optb": "The emission of electromagnetic radiation from the target", "optc": "both (a) and (b)", "optd": "Neither (a) nor (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "\"An Electromagnetic wave falls on to a boundary between two loss less homogeneous media with different refractive indices, a part of the wave is reflected back to the incident medium and the rest is transmitted on to the second media\". This phenomenon is known as :", "opta": "Fresnel reflection", "optb": "Fresnel refraction", "optc": "Snell's law", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following relationship between the wave length (\u03bb), and frequency and the speed (C) of the electromagnetic wave is correct ?", "opta": "C = v + \u03bb", "optb": "", "optc": "C = v\u03bb", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The various stages occuring in GPS system are described below :1. Generation of an output to the user2. Detection of the GPS signal3. Processing the data in the built-in-computer4. Decoding the GPS signal.The correct sequence of the stages is :", "opta": "1, 2, 3, 4", "optb": "2, 3, 4, 1", "optc": "2, 4, 3, 1", "optd": "3, 1, 2 , 4", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The reflection of solar energy is characterised by the water content in the leaf, in the reflective optical infrared:", "opta": "visible (0.4 - 0.7 \u03bcm) region", "optb": "near-IR (0.7 - 1.3 \u03bcm) region", "optc": "short wave-IR (1.3 - 2.7 \u03bcm) region", "optd": "None of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one the following is a correct statement?", "opta": "The vertical section of the soil extending into the parent material, is called profile", "optb": "The layers of the soil parallel to the earth surface, are called horizons.", "optc": "The transitional layer between two adjoining horizons, is called boundary.", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The entire range of the electromagnetic spectrum spans a large spectrum of wave lengths varying from:", "opta": "10-10 to 106 m", "optb": "10-8 to 106 m", "optc": "10-10 to 1010 m", "optd": "10-8 to 108 m", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following :", "opta": "Topology describes the geometric characteristic of objects which do not change under transformations and are independent of any coordinate system", "optb": "Topological characteristics of an object are independent of scale measurement", "optc": "The three elements of topology are adjacency, containment, and connectivity", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which one of the following parameters is considered to determine the reflectance of a vegetation canopy", "opta": "Solar zenith angle", "optb": "Azimuth angle", "optc": "Look angle", "optd": "Number and arrangement of leaves", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A reduction of nitrogen nutrient in plants :", "opta": "affects leaf colour", "optb": "reduces pigment concentration", "optc": "increase the visible reflectivity", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "The surface defined by the locus of points having same phase, is called a wave front.", "optb": "The wave whose surface of constant phase are parallel planes, is known as a plane wave.", "optc": "The relative phase difference between the waves is important and not the absolute phase of a point on the wave", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Leaf reflactance depends primarily on :", "opta": "the pigments", "optb": "internal cell structure", "optc": "equivalent water content", "optd": "All of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following", "opta": "The ratio of the up flux and down flux just above the snow surface, is called albedo", "optb": "Spectral albedo of snow is calculated for the semi-infinite snow thickness", "optc": "Water equivalent height of snow is the height of water column obtained by melting snow.", "optd": "A homogeneous snow pack is one whose average grain size does not vary with depth.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "Permeability is a measure of conducting the magnetic lines of force in the material.", "optb": "Permeability is a measure of the extent to which magnetic lines of force can penetrate a medium.", "optc": "Permeability is expressed as the ratio of the magnetic flux density (B) to the field strength of the magnetizing field.", "optd": "The force between the magnetic poles is inversely proportional to the permeability of the medium.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Pick up the correct statement from the following:", "opta": "In remote sensing technique, the observation place, is called a platform", "optb": "Platforms may be either stationary or mobile", "optc": "Spatial resolution of the imaging system becomes poorer with increase of platform height.", "optd": "Area coverage of the imaging system increases with the increase of the platform altitude.", "opte": "All of these", "ans": "E", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}